Samuel Holten Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Samuel Holten Papers 1630-1843 (bulk 1744-1843)
MSS26419
Holten, Samuel, 1738-1816
2,000 items
4 containers
1.6 linear feet
4 microfilm reels
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Delegate to the United States Continental Congress from and United States representative of Massachusetts, jurist, and physician. Correspondence, account books, and bills and receipts relating primarily to Holten's public service career in Massachusetts, the federal government, and his medical practice.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Adams, Samuel, 1722-1803--Correspondence.; Bowdoin, James, 1726-1790--Correspondence.; Cushing, William, 1732-1810--Correspondence.; Dane, Nathan, 1752-1835--Correspondence.; Gerry, Elbridge, 1744-1814--Correspondence.; Gordon, William, 1728-1807--Correspondence.; Gorham, Nathaniel, 1738-1796--Correspondence.; Hancock, John, 1737-1793--Correspondence.; Holten, Samuel, 1738-1816.; Hutchinson, Israel, 1727 or 1728-1811--Correspondence.; Lowell, John, 1743-1802--Correspondence.; Partridge, George, 1740-1828--Correspondence.; Sullivan, James, 1744-1808--Correspondence.; Wadsworth, Benjamin, 1750-1826--Correspondence.; Wallcut, Thomas, 1758-1840--Correspondence.
Organizations
Massachusetts. Council.; Massachusetts. Provincial Congress.; United States. Congress. House.; United States. Continental Congress.
Subjects
Medicine--Practice--Massachusetts.
Places
Danvers (Mass.)--Social life and customs.; Massachusetts--Politics and government--1775-1865.; United States--Politics and government--1775-1783.; United States--Politics and government--1783-1809.
Occupations
Delegates, U.S. Continental Congress--Massachusetts.; Judges.; Physicians.; Representatives, U.S. Congress--Massachusetts.
Provenance
The papers of Samuel Holten, delegate to the United States Continental Congress from and United States representative of Massachusetts, jurist, and physician, were purchased by the Library of Congress between the years 1908 and 1994.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Samuel Holten are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Microfilm
A microfilm edition of part of these papers is available on four reels. Consult a reference librarian in the Manuscript Division concerning availability for purchase or interlibrary loan.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1738, June 9 Born, Salem Village, later Danvers, Mass.
circa 1756 Practiced medicine, Gloucester, Mass.
1758 Married Mary Warner Returned to medical practice, Danvers, Mass.
1768 1776 Member, Massachusetts General Court
1774 Represented Danvers in Essex County, Mass., convention
1775 Represented Essex County, Mass., in Provincial Congress; appointed to Committee of Safety
1778 1780 Massachusetts delegate, Continental Congress
1781 Signer, Articles of Confederation Incorporator, Massachusetts Medical Society
1782 1787 Massachusetts delegate, Continental Congress
1785 Joined with Elbridge Gerry and Rufus King in refusing to present to Congress the Massachusetts Resolves requesting revision of the Articles of Confederation
1788 Anti-federalist delegate to Massachusetts convention on the Constitution
1793 1795 Member, United States House of Representatives
1796 1815 Judge of probate, Essex County, Mass.
1812 1813 One of early founders of temperance movement in Massachusetts
1816, Jan. 2 Died, Danvers, Mass.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Samuel Holten (1738-1816) span the years 1630-1843, with the bulk of the items concentrated in the period 1744-1843. The collection consists of correspondence, account books, and bills and receipts. The correspondence relates chiefly to Holten's service in the Massachusetts Provincial General Court, Massachusetts Governor's Council, Continental Congress, and United States House of Representatives. Other papers relate to his medical practice and to his life and work in Danvers, Massachusetts. Correspondents include Samuel Adams, James Bowdoin, William Cushing, Nathan Dane, Elbridge Gerry, William Gordon, Nathaniel Gorham, John Hancock, Israel Hutchinson, John Lowell, George Partridge, James Sullivan, and Thomas Wallcut.
The addition to the papers of Samuel Holten spans the years 1783-1785 and consists of draft copies of Holten's correspondence, including letters to William Cushing, Elbridge Gerry, and Benjamin Wadsworth, and a letter from Thomas Wallcut to Holten.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged by type of material.
Container List
Available on microfilm. Shelf no. 16,046
- Correspondence (Box 1, Reel 1)
  - 1630-1660, 1744-1749, 1753-1790, (15 folders) (Box 1, Reel 1)
  - 1791-1816, undated, (16 folders) (Box 2, Reel 2)
- Financial papers (Reel 3)
  - Legal fees, 1796-1811, (4 folders) (Box 3, Reel 3)
  - Bills, accounts, and receipts (Box 3, Reel 3)
    - 1744-1793, (9 folders) (Box 3, Reel 3)
    - 1794-1843, undated, (8 folders) (Box 4, Reel 4)
- Addition (Box 4)
  - Correspondence, 1783-1785 (Box 4)